announcement of my new book
where I will build a personal assistant from scratch.
I don't know if this is the title of the book, but this is like
what you will do throughout the book.
And basically as I said it will be
an announcement of the book and
at this point I just want to say that I
will do it again with
Maxim. I don't want to say anything about the publisher
yet, so I want to keep it a little bit mysterious at this
point, just that it's a new book on building a personal
assistant from scratch together with Maxim
and then I want to like quickly explain
what I will build, because this is also a sponsor
post for mongodb, so I need to
like show at a very high level
everything that we'll build in the book with the help
of mongodb as our unified memory. So I already
have this diagram in place, so basically you can just walk around what's
going on in here. So everything starts with
the data pipeline where we just get this input to
different type of URIs from multiple sources
such as a Puginface, Substack, Medium,
LinkedIn, Custom Sides, basically
any type of URIs as input. We process them with
different type of specialized ETLs and normalize
them as a document, which will be stored
inside the data warehouse, which
is still a mongodb collection of
documents, tracking the metadata of everything,
of the source of the document basically.
And the next step is to process the document through the memory pipeline where
we have a graph extractor where we extract entities and relationships,
then we have this normalization step where we check the
current knowledge graph if that entity already
exists or not. We're using various methods, so it doesn't matter
at this point because we keep it high level, right? But we
use like fuzzy search and semantic
search techniques plus aliasing to
find if the entity already exists inside the memory, and
then we use an embedding model on top of the content
of the chunk or document that has
been processed to create the embedding.
And we will use Voyage AI for this particular
use case, which is Voyage AI by MongoDB.
So they come coupled together very nicely, so
they work together very nicely. And the final output
are these knowledge graph objects which will be stored into the
unified memory powered by
MongoDB. And this unified memory is made
out of short-term memory, long-term
memory, and reasoning memory,
right? And everything is bundled
together via a knowledge graph.
The short-term memory contains like a past and current
conversations, messages. The long-term memory contains
basically the semantic and episodic memory, which is the actual
knowledge graph such as people that you know, preferences,
episodes, documents, and all of that is part of the long-term
memory. And the reasoning memory
contains like past traces where the agent
already explored specific scenarios
and it makes inside these traces
which one were correct and which one were
wrong. So when the agent tries, so when a user asks the agent
to do something similar, it already knows what
path is good and what path is wrong, similar to reinforcement
learning, like continual reinforcement learning,
right? Okay. And the next step,
on the other side, we have this point
four where we fine tune small language
models like this is what SLM stands for, small
language model. We fine tune them via SFD and
reinforcement learning which stands for supervised
fine tuning and reinforcement learning. So we fine
tune small specialized models for this graphic extraction
step, specialized on our data and use case and domain
implicitly, right? And we create,
we fine tune and host these models for this graphic
structure where we want to extract
entities and relationships based on our
ontology and not other ontology,
so our specific ontology. So we also show
this step basically how to fine tune small models
for particular elements of this
whole architecture which you can later on adapt
and fine tune on different elements such as if you have
something here in the data pipeline for cleaning or the embedding
model or some here in the tools or some small
models from the harness, that's the point.
Or for example here from the query when we
want to decode a natural language query into
something that's queryable inside MongoDB and basically you can use the same
techniques to do that as
well. And then we output the small language model
inside this graphic structure step to basically
will be part of the memory pipeline. And I realized that
I messed up the numbers here, so we have two fives.
I will correct this after this video, so
basically the numbers will not match what I'm showing
you here, I will correct that, but you can just follow
the new numbers afterwards because the concepts
will be the same. Okay so this is more on the data
pipeline, memory pipeline, fine tuning pipeline
side of things like the backend and next on the user facing
part of things we have this Tui, this harness and SAP
server. And the story begins at the Tui
which stands for terminal user interface
where basically a user interacts with the harness
through the CLI similar to cloud code and it asks
the harness which is more or less made
out of an LLM plus the tools such as
a bash tools, a grab tools, to do,
keeping track of a to do list tools
and things like that. Basically tools
that allow you, allows the harness to
interact with your computer and to generate code and
plan, more or less these are the core family of tools.
And then we also implement, so we will implement all of these from scratch starting from
the Tui to this LLM loop and also the skills with
progressive disclosure, so we will implement,
show how to implement skills from scratch with progressive disclosure.
So all of this is implemented from scratch, not using cloud
code or also using cloud code plus how to implement
all of this from scratch. And also we'll
show how to hook this as an MCP client, the harness
is an MCP client to the MCP server like the
continual learning memory MCP server which
will have these tools to query the memory,
right, like do simple queries using the
graph, vector and text search and do normal
more compact queries or do deep research
queries for more in-depth traversals
and knowledge work and also ingest any type
of URI similar to here from the data pipeline
on demand directly from the harness or also
ingest the query conversation basically to learn
from the conversation between you
the user and the agent. Okay,
so this is basically point nine and
point ten and the last step will be this
AI this layer
which is actually
observability
which is like monitoring plus evals.
I will fix this afterwards to look nice but the idea is that we will also have this
observability layer where we will do monitoring
for the MCP server and the harness.
I still have to think this through in more detail but the idea is
that we will have monitoring and evals to actually
see that our harness, our special
eye harness actually works well as
a harness per se but also couples with MCP
server for continual memory and that also
works on specialized domains such as keeping conversation
or generating articles or writing code or whatever
domains that we want to specialize in.
So yeah, this is like a walkthrough of what we
will build and all of this will be built from
scratch just using like MongoDB for the database like the data
warehouse and the unified memory and prefact-fasting
MCP as the MCP server and Voyage AI as the embedding
model but focus this post for MongoDB
because this is a sponsor post for MongoDB
and only MongoDB and Voyage AI are their products.
Otherwise keep everything else just a tooth-free,
just conceptually walk over all of this.
[end of transcript] [ Silence
]